<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<table width="100%">
			<tr>
				<td valign="top" align="right"  width="20%">
					<br/>
					<a name="about">&#160;</a>
					<font class="negrito" size="-1">about this site&#160;&#160;&#160;</font>
				</td>
				<td width="70%">
					<br/>
					<br/>
					<br/>
					<font class="nomodel" size="-1">
						
      <p> <b>SciELO Latin American Social Sciences Journals English Edition</b> 
        is a product of a joint effort of <a href="http://www.scielo.org">SciELO</a> 
        (Scientific Electronic Library Online) and the <a href="http://www.centroedelstein.org.br/english/index.asp" target="_blank">The 
        Edelstein Center for Social Research</a>, with the support of the Open 
        Society Institute (OSI).</p>
						<br/>
						<br/>
						
      <p align="center"> <a href="http://www.centroedelstein.org.br/english/index.asp" target="_blank"> 
        <img alt="The Edelstein Center for Social Research" border="0" src="/img/en/glogo_Edelstein.gif"/> 
        </a> </p>
						<br/>
						<br/>
						<p>
The objective of <b>SciELO Latin American Social Sciences Journals English
Edition</b> is to contribute to the promotion of international access to Latin American scientific journals in Social Sciences. Its main characteris­tic is to make available English full texts, <i>at no charge to the public</i>, in order to increase Latin America Social Sciences visibility and accessibility.</p>
						<p>In its first phase the site will include 30 journals, from Argentina, Bolivia, Brazil, Chile, Paraguay and Uruguay. During the coming months will be adding monthly four journals.</p>
						<p>
							<b>SciELO Latin American Social Sciences Journals English
Edition</b> uses SciELO Methodology developed by <a href="http://www.fapesp.br">FAPESP</a> - Fundação de Amparo à
Pesquisa do Estado de São Paulo, in partnership with <a href="http://www.bireme.br/bvs/I/ihome.htm">BIREME</a> - Latin American and Caribbean
 Center on Health Sciences Information. Since 2002, the Project is also supported
by <a href="http://www.cnpq.br">CNPq</a>
- Conselho Nacional de Desenvolvimento Científico e Tecnológico.</p>
					</font>
					<br/>
					<br/>
				</td>
				<td width="10%">&#160;</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td valign="top" align="right"  width="20%">
					<a name="help">&#160;</a>
					<font class="negrito" size="-1">help&#160;&#160;&#160;</font>
				</td>
				<td width="70%">
					<font class="nomodel" size="-1">
						<p>
							<b>SciELO Latin American Social Sciences Journals English
Edition</b> interface provides access to its journals collection through an <i>alphabetic
list</i> of titles or a <i>subject list</i> or a word <i>search </i>of the
journal title, publisher names, city of publication and subject.<br/>
							<br/>
The interface also provides access to fulltext articles through <i>author index</i> or
<i>subject index</i>, or a <i>search </i>on article elements such as author
names, words from title, subject, words from text and year of publication.<br/>
							<br/>
Click at the hypertext link at the <a href="#top">top</a> to have access to the corresponding access
pages.</p>
						<br/>
					</font>
					<br/>
					<br/>
					<br/>
				</td>
				<td width="10%">&#160;</td>
			</tr>
		</table>
